Finding Aid for University of Michigan Alumnae Club of Ann Arbor. Sara Browne Smith Group Records 1930-1995
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
University of Michigan Alumnae Club of Ann Arbor. Sara Browne Smith Group records 1930-1995
University of Michigan Alumnae Club of Ann Arbor. Sara Browne Smith Group.
1 oversize volumes
3 linear feet
8711 BIMU H62
Organization of Ann Arbor, Michigan alumnae of the University of Michigan, sponsors scholarships, supported a cooperative house for women students; papers include officer's and committee files, publicity and events files and photographs, and a history of the Sarah Browne Smith Group.
Bentley Historical Library University of Michigan
The records were donated to the Bentley Historical Library by the Sara Browne Smith Group (Donor No. 6715 ) in 1977. Periodic additions have been received.
The record group is open for research.
In 1931, Mrs. Sara Browne Smith (nee Sara Spencer Browne), an alumna of the University of Michigan and former chairman of the Alumnae Council, was instrumental in the formation of the first University of Michigan alumnae club in Ann Arbor. Mrs. Alva Gordon Sink was asked to organize the group, and an initial organizational meeting was held on November 5, 1931. The first membership reception and tea was held on December 5, 1931; 173 attended, and 136 paid dues of one dollar each. The founding president was Alva Gordon Sink. In March 1932, a Scholarship Committee was established "to aid deserving Ann Arbor girls who wished to attend the University of Michigan." The funding of scholarships would become a primary focus for the Smith group over the succeeding decades, as would the financial support that they gave to the Center for the Continuing Education of Women, the Henderson House, and the national Alumnae Council.
In 1938, by which time the membership had reached 552, the group was named the Ann Arbor Michigan Alumnae Club. Its next major project, following the establishment of the Scholarship Committee, was the financing of "a cooperative dormitory for women, modeled somewhat on the lines of the present Alumnae House, to be known as Henderson House, a memorial to Mrs. W.D. Henderson" (Michigan Alumnus, Oct. 1937). Henderson House was completed in September 1945. The Ann Arbor Michigan Alumnae Club had donated $2000 to the effort from 1937 to 1940, and continued to give financial support through financial support through scholarships for room and board.
In 1946, an offshoot of the Ann Arbor Michigan Alumnae Club, consisting of younger members, was organized as the Lucile B. Conger Group. In 1953, part of the Conger Group was reorganized as the Margaret Lawler Waterman Group. These groups (with the Ann Arbor Michigan Alumnae Club) worked both together and separately, but there was some confusion about the names, and a desire to make the groups equal under the umbrella name of the University of Michigan Alumnae Club of Ann Arbor. By 1954, therefore, the Ann Arbor Michigan Alumnae Club was renamed the Sara Browne Smith Group. In 1960, another group was organized, named for Alva Gordon Sink; these four groups (Smith, Conger, Waterman, and Sink) formed part of the University of Michigan Alumnae Club of Ann Arbor.
By the 1990s, the membership of the group had decreased substantially (with 54 members in 1994). In a letter to the Alumnae Council, the governing board of the Sara Browne Smith Group wrote: "With the decline in membership and the aging of the remaining members it has become increasingly difficult to recruit leadership....Our usual attendance is 15 including the board. In addition, we are unable to fulfill our mission: providing new monies for scholarships." The group requested, and was granted (April 22, 1995), status as an "Emerita Club"; the group would no longer have meetings or pay dues, but it retained a representative on the Alumnae Council. The remaining funds of the group were incorporated into the Sara Browne Smith Scholarship fund, managed by the Alumni Association, and a "Celebration" of the group's years of service and new Emerita status was held on May 21, 1995.
A more detailed history, up to 1981, was published as Sara Browne Smith and Friends, available in the first series of this record group; this is the source for most of the above information.
1997 Accessions including material from 1930 to 1960
1981 Accessions including material from 1947-1981
1996 Accessions divided into seven series:
Historical Information
Officers' Files
Committees' Files
Miscellaneous Administrative Files
Publicity Files
Events Files
Photographs
The records of the University of Michigan Alumnae Club of Ann Arbor Sara Browne Smith Group include minutes, reports, scrapbooks, correspondence, and other materials relating to group activities.
1977 and 1981 Accessions. The 1977 accession includes material from 1930 to 1960, while the 1981 accession documents the period 1947-1981. The contents of these accessions are not further described in this Scope and Content Note.
1996 Accession. The records of this accession of the Sara Browne Smith Group are divided into seven series: historical information; officers' files; committees' files; miscellaneous administrative files; publicity files; events file; and photographs.
Subject:
Ann Arbor (Mich.); Smith, Sara Browne.; University of Michigan. Alumnae Club.; University of Michigan--Alumni and alumnae.; Women--Michigan--Ann Arbor--Societies and clubs.; University of Michigan Alumnae Club of Ann Arbor. Sara Browne Smith Group.
Form and Genre Terms:
Scrapbooks.; Photographs.
- 1977 Accession
  - Minutes and Membership lists 1931-1960
    - Minute book, November 1931-May 1945 (Box 1)
      (include membership lists, 1932-33, 1944-45, and 1946-47)
    - Notebook of minutes July 1945-1949/50 (Box 1)
    - Notebook of minutes October 1950-1953/54;, September 1957-1959, 1959-60 (Box 1)
      (incomplete)
    - Minutes and membership material 1954-1955 (Box 1)
    - Minutes 1955/56-1956/57 (Box 1)
    - Council material 1957-1958 (Box 1)
  - Scrapbooks
    - 1930-1941 (Box 1)
    - 1937-1938 (Box 1)
    - 1939-1940 (Box 1)
    - 1942-1945 (Box 1)
- 1981 Accession
  - Minutes, Membership List and Reports
    - Notebook of minutes, February 1960-May 1967 (Box 2)
    - Minutes, 1967/68-1978/79 (Box 2)
    - Notebook of president (Alison Myers) 1976-78 (Box 2)
    - Membership lists 1955/56-1980/81 (Box 2)
    - Newsletters 1948/49-Spring 1979/80 (Box 2)
    - Treasurer's reports 1963-1979 (Box 2)
    - Scrapbook 1947-1977 (Volume 1)
    - Committee reports
      - Ann Arbor Joint Coordinating Board 1967-1974 (Box 2)
      - Constitution and bylaws 1955-1977 (Box 2)
      - Membership 1949-1975 (Box 2)
      - Scholarship 1962-1969, 1974/75-1978/79 (Box 2)
      - Social 1963-1976 (Box 2)
      - Ways and Means 1973-1977 (Box 2)
  - Audio-cassette interviews with
    - Byers, Ruth Rankin September 1981 (Box 2)
    - Eberbach, Linda August 1981 (Box 2)
    - Sink, Alva Gordon May-June 1981 (Box 2)
    - Walz, Catherine Kalder May 1981 (Box 2)
- 1996 Accession
  - Historical information
    (see also biography of Sara Browne Smith in Athletic Chairman's file)
    - Sara Browne Smith and Friends, by Anne Vance Hatcher, 1981 (Box 3)
    - "News and Views of the Sara Browne Smith Alumnae Group, 1982-1992" (Box 3)
      (annotated with identification of individuals)
    - Scrapbook: clippings, newsletters, etc. 1971-1981 (Box 3)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 3)
  - Officers' files
    - President
      - Elizabeth K. Davenport 1979-80 (Box 3)
      - Pauline Ferguson 1980-81, 2 folders (Box 3)
    - Secretary 1979-1983 (Box 3)
    - Athletic Chairman 1977-1982 (Box 3)
    - Historian 1979-1982 (Box 3)
  - Committees' files
    - Membership Committee
      - circa 1975-1981 (Box 3)
      - 1977-1981 (Box 3)
    - Scholarship Committee circa 1958-1979, 1977-1978 (Box 3)
  - Miscellaneous administrative files
    - Alumni Association and related groups: miscellaneous material circa 1980-1994 (Box 3)
    - "Emerita" status (Box 3)
    - Financial records circa 1985-1995 (Box 3)
    - Governing Board
      - Minutes, agendas and reports 1978-1995 (Box 3)
      - Lists of members of governing board 1986-87, 1989-90 (Box 3)
      - Position descriptions June 1977 (Box 3)
    - Membership lists 1969-1995 (Box 3)
  - Publicity files
    - Newsletters 1970-1995 (Box 3)
    - Newspaper clippings 1979-1981 (Box 3)
      (collected by Pauline Ferguson)
    - Miscellaneous material relating to publicity (Box 3)
  - Files relating to events
    - "First Ladies on Parade" January 11, 1977 (Box 3)
    - Antique show
      - 1978 (Box 3)
      - 1979 (Box 3)
      - 1979 (Box 3)
      - Declarations of gift of proceeds, etc. 1979-1981 (Box 3)
    - Fiftieth Anniversary 1980-1981 (Box 3)
    - Miscellaneous material relating to events (Box 3)
  - Photographs
    - Photographic prints [album] and negatives (originally in possession of Pauline Ferguson), individuals not identified circa 1984 (Box 3)
    - Photographs (with negatives) of Emerita Celebration (Box 3)
    - May 21, 1995 (Box 3)
      (originally in possession of Pauline Ferguson)
    - Negatives and one print (Box 3)
      (probably by Nita Eggertsen)
    - Photographs (2) used in 1981 history:
      - Sara Browne Smith 1923 (Box 3)
      - Alva Gordon Sink and Pauline Ferguson 1981 (Box 3)